David Flavel Jamison papers WLU.Coll.0056
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
David Flavel Jamison papers
Inclusive 1860-1864
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
Jamison, D. F. (David Flavel), 1810-1864
Keitt, Lawrence M. (Lawrence Massillon), 1824-1864
Barnwell, Robert Woodward
WLU.Coll.0056
125 Item 1 Box, 10 folders
Box 1
Folder 1-10
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Vanse W. Marshall in 1928.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes correspondence while Jamison was Secretary of War of South Carolina, 1861; scattered letters and papers pertaining to the South Carolina Secession Convention of which he was president, and papers related to his tenure as presiding judge of the military court of Gen. Beauregard's Corps, 1862-1864. Robert Woodward Barnwell and Lawrence Massillon Keitt are among the correspondents.
South Carolina; South Carolina -- Charleston -- Fort Sumter; Political science; Correspondence; Secession; United States -- Confederate States of America; Military courts; Confederate States of America; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893
- Control (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1860-01-01-1860-12-31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Folder 2 contains documents from early in the Confederacy during South Carolina's secession. Included in this folder are reports on Charleston Harbor defenses and plans for taking Fort Sumter. Along with plans for Fort Sumter, there are also early application letters from General Abraham Meyers and Mexican-American war veterans from the Palmetto Regiment. Also among these papers is the first report from Robert W. Barnwell (whose vote made Jefferson Davis president of the CSA) conferring with the National Government in Washington D.C.
  Thomas, John P., 1833-1912; Smith, Robert P.; Huguenin, Thomas Abram, 1839-1897; Pickens, F. W. (Francis Wilkinson); Limehouse, Edward Just, 1835-1910; Pope, Joseph James, Jr.; Stevens, Peter F. (Peter Fayssoux Stevens), 1830-1910; Gist, William Henry, 1807 - 1874; Anderson, Robert, Major, 1805 - 1871; Manigault, Edward, 1817-1874; Schnierle, John, 1808 - 1861; Myers, Abraham C. (Abraham Charles Myers), 1811 - 1889; Barnwell, Robert Woodward, 1801-1882; DeSaussure, Wilmot G. (Wilmot Gibbes), 1822-1886; Gwynn, Walter, 1802-1882; Pettigrew, James Johnston, 1828-1863; Easterly, John M.; Rivers, Constant Henry, Lieutenant Colonel, 1828-1900; Hayne, Paul Hamilton, 1830-1886; Hernandez, James. J.; Magrath, A. G. (Andrew Gordon), 1813-1893; Memminger, C. G. (Christopher Gustavus), 1803-1888; Dunovant, R. G. M. (Richard Gill Mills), 1821-1898; Citadel. the Military College of South Carolina; South Carolina--Charleston County; South Carolina--Charleston--Fort Sumter; South Carolina--Charleston--Castle Pinckney; South Carolina--Morris Island; South Carolina--Fort Johnson; South Carolina--Summerville; United States. Army. South Carolina Regiment; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 2nd; 1st Regiment, South Carolina Artillery. Lafayette Artillery Company; Fort Palmetto; South Carolina--Orangeburg County; South Carolina--Columbia; South Carolina--Fort Moultrie; Arsenal Academy (Columbia, S.C.); Louisiana--New Orleans; South Carolina--Charleston Harbor; South Carolina--Charleston
- Correspondence, 1861-01-01-1861-01-31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Jamison, D. F. (David Flavel), 1810-1864; Burnett Rhett, Andrew, 1833-1879; Burnett, Burgh S.; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 1st. Irish Volunteers; Planter's Hotel; Citadel. the Military College of South Carolina; Georgia Military Institute (Marietta, Ga.); Manget, Victor H., 1837-1919; State Rights and Free Trade Party (S.C.); South Carolina--Charleston County; South Carolina--Morris Island; South Carolina--Charleston--Fort Sumter; Pettigrew, James Johnston, 1828-1863; South Carolina--Charleston--Castle Pinckney; Myers, Abraham C. (Abraham Charles Myers), 1811 - 1889; Branch, John Luther, 1825-1894; Mississippi--Jackson; Pickens, F.W. (Francis Wilkinson), 1805-1869; National Hotel (Washington, D.C.); Camden, John; Spratt, L.W. (Leonidas William), 1818-1903; Morris Island Lighthouse (S.C.); Vigilant Rifle Company (1860-1861); Charleston (South Carolina) German Artillery; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 2nd; Manigault, Edward, 1817-1874; Washington Light Infantry (Charleston, S.C.); D. B. Vincent; Simonton, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1829-1904; Atlantic Ocean--Stono Inlet; 1st Regiment, South Carolina Artillery. Lafayette Artillery Company; Mills, S. S.; South Carolina--Charleston Harbor; South Carolina--Charleston; Georgia--Macon; Nullification (States' rights); Branham, W. H.; South Carolina--Fort Moultrie; South Carolina--Fort Johnson; South Carolina--James Island; Gwynn, Walter, 1802-1882; Simons, James, 1813-1879; Dunovant, R. G. M. (Richard Gill Mills), 1821-1898; Ripley, R. S. (Roswell Sabine), 1823-1887; Dozier, William Gaillard, 1833-1908; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 4th; Cunningham, John, 1805-1869; Carter, W. D.; White Point Garden; Aldrich, N., Reverend; King, Henry Campbell, 1819-1862; Pope, Joseph James, Jr., 1825-1870; Gist, States Rights, 1831-1864; Meyerhoff, B., Lieutenant; South Carolina--Folly Island (Island); White, E. B. (Edward Brickell), 1806-1882; McLaws, Lafayette, 1821-1897; South Carolina--Cummings Point; Trapier, James H., 1815-1865; Jamison, Sander Glover, 1830-1900; 33rd Regiment South Carolina Militia; Ferguson, Thomas B., 1841-1922; Ferguson, Thomas B., 1841-1922; Rose, James; South Carolina--Sullivans Island; Foster, John G. (John Gray), 1823-1874; Washington (South Carolina) Artillery; Walter, George H.; Alabama--Tuscaloosa; Orr, James Lawrence, 1822-1873; Parrott, R. P. (Robert Parker), 1804-1877; West Point Foundry Association; Gibbon, John, 1827-1896; Clay, C. C. (Clement Claiborne), 1816-1882; Lynah, Arthur M.; Lesesne, Henry Deas, 1810-1886; Heyward, Nathaniel Barnwell, 1816-1891; Short, Emanuel; Guard, A.C.; Bryan, Edward B.; Vanderhorst, Louis M., 1832-1864; Martin, William E.; Screven, John H., 1823-1903; Capers, Francis W., 1819-1896; Fort Palmetto; Hamilton, James; Farley, H. S.; Yates, Joseph A.; Gourdin, Robert N., 1812-1894; Macbeth, Charles, 1805-1881; Washington (D.C.); Rice, Henry M. (Henry Mower), 1816-1894; Chesnut, James, 1815-1885; Baker, Edward Dickinson, 1811-1861; Quinn, Thomas, 1828-1903; Quinn, Patrick, 1822-1886; Brady, Edward W., Jr.; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Regiment of Rifles, 1st. Company G; Schooner Petrel; Lightship Rattlesnake Shoal; DeSaussure, Wilmot G. (Wilmot Gibbes), 1822-1886; Floating batteries
- Correspondence, 1861-02-01-1861-02-28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  South Carolina--Charleston; Jamison, D. F. (David Flavel), 1810-1864; Pickens, F.W. (Francis Wilkinson), 1805-1869; White, E. B. (Edward Brickell), 1806-1882; Floating batteries; Davega, Columbus, 1830-1882; Siege of Sevastopol' (Sevastopol', Ukraine: 1854-1855); de Treville, Richard, Sr., 1801-1874; South Carolina. Militia; South Carolina. General Assembley; Cooper, Samuel, 1798-1876; Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866; Hardee, William Joseph, 1815-1873; Buchanan, James, 1791-1868; Confederate States of America. War Department; Confederate States of America; Keitt, Lawrence M. (Lawrence Massillon), 1824-1864; Alabama--Montgomery; American Civil War (United States :1861-1865); Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 10th; South Carolina--Georgetown; South Carolina--Fort Moultrie; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 2nd; Henning, Norman Phillip; South Carolina--Santee River; South Carolina--Murrells Inlet Region; Daggett, Thomas West, Captain, 1828-1893; Waccamaw Light Artillery; South Carolina--Little River; Litchfield, John L., Captain; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 7th; 33rd Regiment South Carolina Militia; Austin, Charles; South Carolina--Morris Island; South Carolina--Sullivans Island; South Carolina--Mars Bluff; South Carolina--Florence; South Carolina--Richmond; North Carolina--Wilmington; Harllee, W. W. (William Wallace), 1812-1897; Gwynn, Walter, 1802-1882; Confederate States of America. Ordnance Bureau; Parrott gun; South Carolina--Charleston Harbor; Manigault, Gabriel E. (Gabriel Edward), 1833-1899; Lynch, Arthur M.; Crawford, Samuel Wylie, 1827-1892; Washington Fire Company; German Rifle Company; Lafar, John J., 1797-1873; South Carolina--Fort Johnson; Martin, Robert; Hagood, Johnson, 1829-1898; Lee, Francis D., 1826-1885; South Carolina--Charleston--Castle Pinckney; South Carolina--Cummings Point; Virginia--Richmond; Tredegar Iron Works (Richmond, Va); White Point Garden; Citadel. the Military College of South Carolina; J. M. Eason & Brother; Atlantic Ocean--Winyah Bay; Glaze, William, 1815-1883; Palmetto Armory; Henerey, William S.; South Carolina--Beaufort; Cameron, Archibald, 1813-1881; Lufburrow and Timmons co.; R&J Lacklison; A. N. Miller; Linville & Smedley; Watervilet Arsenal; U. S. Arsenal; South Carolina--State Arsenal; South Carolina Coast Police; Arsenal Academy (Columbia, S.C.); Virginia--Petersburg; Louisiana--New Orleans; Coles Island; Florida--Pensacola; Hazard Powder Company; Charleston Arsenal; Schooner Stowell Cobb; Schooner Helene; Schooner Petrel; Schooner William Aiken; General Clinch (Ship); Steam Tug Aid; Catawba (ship); Lynch, Thomas M.
- Correspondence, 1861-03-01-1861-03-31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  South Carolina--Charleston--Fort Sumter; Jamison, D. F. (David Flavel), 1810-1864; Lynch, Thomas M.; South Carolina--Charleston; Anderson, Robert, Major, 1805 - 1871; Lynch, Arthur M.; Crawford, Samuel Wylie, 1827-1892; Hall, Norman J., 1842-1867; Fort Palmetto; Pope, Joseph James, Jr., 1825-1870; Pickens, F.W. (Francis Wilkinson), 1805-1869; South Carolina--Morris Island; Gregg, Maxcy, 1814-1862; United States. Army. South Carolina Volunteers, 1st (1862-1864); Pettigrew, James Johnston, 1828-1863; Rooney, M. E.; Washington (D.C.); Washington Family; Washington, L. Quinton; Wigfall, Louis T. (Louis Trezevant), 1816-1874; Barbot, Anthony, 1834-1882; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Illinois--Springfield; "House Divided" speech; Indiana--Indianapolis; Lincoln's Indiannapolis speech; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872; Sherman, John, 1823-1900; United States--New York Harbor; Florida--Fort Pickens; Pawnee (Ship); Philadelphia Naval Shipyard (Philadelphia, Pa.); First inauguration of Abraham Lincoln; Florida--Pensacola; North Carolina--Fort Anderson; Virginia--Richmond; Virginia--Alexandria; North Island Redoubt; South Carolina--North Island; Brooks Guard; Alston, Thomas Pinckney, 1795-1861; Kaminski, Heiman, 1839-1923; Norman, J. H. (James Henry), 1829-1877; South Carolina--Winnsboro; Charleston Floating Battery; Rion, James H. (James Henry), 1828-1886; Macbeth, E. W.; Gist, States Rights, 1831-1864; DeSaussure, Wilmot G. (Wilmot Gibbes), 1822-1886; Capers, Ellison, 1837-1908; Washington Light Infantry (Charleston, S.C.); Thomas, Captain; Citadel. the Military College of South Carolina; South Carolina--State Arsenal; South Carolina--Fort Moultrie; South Carolina--Sullivans Island; South Carolina. Constitutional Convention; Arthur, B. F. (Benjamin Franklin), Sr., 1826-1870; South Carolina Seccession Convention; Gwynn, Walter, 1802-1882; Lee, Francis D., 1826-1885; South Carolina--Fort Johnson; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893; South Carolina--Cummings Point; South Carolina--Breach Inlet; South Carolina--Coles Island; Battery Island; South Carolina--Mount Pleasant; South Carolina--James Island; South Carolina--Richmond; South Carolina--Charleston--Castle Pinckney; Dunovant, R. G. M. (Richard Gill Mills), 1821-1898; 5th Regiment South Carolina Militia; Perryman, W. W. (William W.), 1831-1891; Brooks, John Hampden, Captain, 1833-1911; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 7th; Huguenin, Thomas Abram, 1839-1897; Hall, Norman J., 1842-1867; Pundt, J. M.; Dupont, John; Foster, John G. (John Gray), 1823-1874; Confederate States of America. Army. Corps of Engineers; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 2nd; Melchers, Alexander, 1831-1885; 1st Regiment, South Carolina Artillery. Lafayette Artillery Company; Atlantic Ocean--Stono Inlet; American Civil War (United States :1861-1865); Maryland--Baltimore
- Correspondence, 1861-04-02-1861-12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Pope, Joseph James, Jr., 1825-1870; 1st Regiment, South Carolina Artillery. Lafayette Artillery Company; Jamison, D. F. (David Flavel), 1810-1864; South Carolina--Sullivans Island; Small, Jacob, Captain; German Rifle Company; South Carolina--Fort Moultrie; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 9th; Gist, States Rights, 1831-1864; Palmetto Riflemen; Dunovant, R. G. M. (Richard Gill Mills), 1821-1898; Ripley, R. S. (Roswell Sabine), 1823-1887; Anderson, Robert, Major, 1805 - 1871; 1st Regiment, South Carolina Artillery. Lafayette Artillery Company; Heinrich, Harms, 1833-1869; Rutledge, Benjamin Huger, 1828-1893; South Carolina--Secessionville; South Carolina--Morris Island; South Carolina--Myrtle Beach; Pettigrew, James Johnston, 1828-1863; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Regiment of Rifles, 1st; South Carolina--Charleston Harbor; South Carolina--Charleston; Gwynn, Walter, 1802-1882; Evans, Nathan George, 1824-1868; Pressley, John G. (John Gotea), 1833-1895; Foster, John G. (John Gray), 1823-1874; Doubleday, Abner, 1819-1893; Confederate States of America. Army. Corps of Engineers; Walker, Joseph, 1835-1902; Pickens, F.W. (Francis Wilkinson), 1805-1869; R & A.P. Caldwell; J. Campsen & Co.; South Carolina. Constitutional Convention; South Carolina Seccession Convention; Ordnance of Secession; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893; Simms, William Gilmore, 1806-1870; South Carolina--Columbia; South Carolina--Beaufort; South Carolina--Colleton County; South Carolina--Georgetown; Porter, Wm. D. (William Dennison), 1810-1883; Simons, James, 1813-1879; Valentine, Jacob; Mexican War (1846-1848); Blanding, William D., 1818-1888; Battle of Churubusco (Mexico City, Mexico: 1847); Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Bennett, J.; Motte Alston Pringle, Jacob, 1827-1886; Robertson, Louis F.; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 2nd; North, Edward; Moses, H.; Colcock, William Ferguson, 1804-1889; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 17th; Cunningham, John; Martin, William Edward, 1815-1869; Lee, Francis D., 1826-1885; South Carolina--James Island; Trapier, James H., 1815-1865
- South Carolina state ordinances and related correspondence, 1862-01-06-1862-12-27 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  South Carolina. General Assembly; Ordnance of Secession; Confederate States of America; South Carolina. Constitutional Convention; South Carolina Seccession Convention; Magrath, A. G. (Andrew Gordon), 1813-1893; Wardlaw, David Lewis, 1799-1873; Dunkin, Benjamin Faneuil, 1792-1874; Barnwell, Robert Woodward, 1801-1882; Rhett, Robert Barnwell, 1800-1876; Ingles, J. A.; Bank of the State of South Carolina; South Carolina--Burwood Plantation; South Carolina--Charleston; Pickens, F.W. (Francis Wilkinson), 1805-1869; Dunovant, R. G. M. (Richard Gill Mills), 1821-1898; South Carolina--Edgefield; South Carolina--Chelsea; Grisham, William Steele, 1824-1878; Hayne, Isaac W. (Isaac William), 1809-1880; Harllee, W. W. (William Wallace), 1812-1897; South Carolina--Columbia; South Carolina; Magrath, A. G. (Andrew Gordon), 1813-1893; South Carolina--Camp Williams; Shingler, William Pinkney, Colonel, 1827-1869; Mercer, Hugh W. (Hugh Weedon), 1808-1877; Ferrill, John O.; Damas, C.A.D.; Georgia--Savannah
- South Carolina military court correspondence, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Georgia--Savannah; Jamison, D. F. (David Flavel), 1810-1864; CSA Military Court (district of South Carolina, Georgia, and Florida); South Carolina--Charleston; Mercer, Hugh W. (Hugh Weedon), 1808-1877; Jordan, Thomas, 1819-1895; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893; Lamar, L. Q. C. (Lucius Quintus Cincinnatus), 1825-1893; Ferrill, John O.; Kearny, E., A.A.A.G. (Acting Assistant Adjutant General); South Carolina--Barnwell County; Fender, William M., 1833-1870; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Cavalry Regiment, 5th; Morgan's Squadron; 5th South Carolina Cavalry Company I (Tiler's/Tyler's Company); Steedly, Moses, 1824-deceased; Steedly, E.; South Carolina--McClellanville; Stokes, Jefferson, 1829-1902; Hunter, J. W.; Smith, Clifton H. (Clifton Hewitt), 1841-1902; Jeffords, Robert J. (Robert Josiah), 1834-1864; Ripley, R. S. (Roswell Sabine), 1823-1887; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 21st; Carlisle, W. H. (William Henry), b. 1819; Waters, Philama B., b. ca.1812; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 2nd; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 27th; Talley, W. H. (William H.), b. ca. 1836; South Carolina; American Civil War (United States :1861-1865); Citadel. the Military College of South Carolina
- South Carolina military court cases, 1863-1864 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Jamison, D. F. (David Flavel), 1810-1864; South Carolina; American Civil War (United States :1861-1865); Abner, Wilson; Villani, Giovanni, ca.1275-1348; Edward, III, King of England, 1312-1377; Battle of Crécy (Crécy-en-Ponthieu, France: 1346); CSA Military Court (district of South Carolina, Georgia, and Florida); Confederate States of America; Confederate States of America. Army. Cavalry; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893; Jordan, Thomas, 1819-1895; Mercer, George, Private; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 25th; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 27th; Confederate States of America. Army. Georgia Light Artillery Battalion, 12th; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 23rd; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry, 22nd; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Battalion, 7th; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Cavalry Regiment, 4th; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 1st. Irish Volunteers; Confederate States of America. Army. Corps of Engineers; Brown, Joseph M.; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Artillery Battalion, 15th (Lucas' Battalion); Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Regiment, 26th; Gist Guard Light Artillery; 1st Regiment, South Carolina Artillery. Lafayette Artillery Company; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Infantry Battalion, 7th; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Palmetto Light Artillery.; Santee Light Artillery; Gilchrist, B. C., AA General; Confederate States of America. Congress.; Confederate Articles of War; Vaus, Richard; Vaus, William; Confederate States of America. Army. Georgia Infantry Regiment, 47th; Confederate States of America. Army. South Carolina Cavalry, 1st; 7th South Carolina Reserve Battalion (Ward's); South Carolina Cavalry Kirk's Squadron; 2nd South Carolina Artillery Regiment; Vanderhorst Street, Charleston, SC; South Carolina--Charleston
- Letters, No Date, fragments (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Jamison, D. F. (David Flavel), 1810-1864; South Carolina--Charleston Harbor; South Carolina--Charleston; Leffmann, William, b. 1836; Confederate States of America. Congress.; Confederate States of America; Confederate States of America. Provisional Congress; Arthur, Benjamin Franklin, 1826-1870; Bonham, Milledge L. (Milledge Luke), 1813-1890; Pickens, F. W. (Francis Wilkinson); Bartow, Francis S. (Francis Stebbins), 1816-1861; Barksdale, William, 1821-1863; Kenan, Augustus Holmes, 1805-1870; Davis, Jefferson; Benjamin, J. P. (Judah Philip), 1811-1884; Jenkins, Albert Gallatin, 1830-1864; Gist Rifles; Gist, States Rights, 1831-1864; Confederate States of America. Army. Hampton Legion; Confederate States of America. Army. Gary's Brigade; Glover, Thomas Jefferson, 1816-1874